<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The kingdomes manifestation: wherein a course may be taken for us and our posterity, to enjoy peace and truth together, with the propagation of the Gospell; with certaine considerations condusing thereunto. Delivered in a speech by Iohn Pym, Esquire: once a worthy member of the House of Commons, now deceased the eighth of December, 1643.</title>
            <author>Pym, John, 1584-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E78_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R940</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873543</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873543</idno>
            <idno type="VID">126020</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91385)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 126020)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 13:E78[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The kingdomes manifestation: wherein a course may be taken for us and our posterity, to enjoy peace and truth together, with the propagation of the Gospell; with certaine considerations condusing thereunto. Delivered in a speech by Iohn Pym, Esquire: once a worthy member of the House of Commons, now deceased the eighth of December, 1643.</title>
                  <author>Pym, John, 1584-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 23, [1] p., [1] leaf of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B.H. and are to be sold by J. West, neere the New-Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The speech is dated: 17 April 1640.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 11th".</note>
                  <note>First page filmed at rear of Wing B1799A, immediately preceding on film.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pym, John, 1584-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:126020:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE KINGDOMES Manifeſtation: WHEREIN A courſe may be taken for us and our poſterity, to enjoy Peace and Truth together, with the propagation of the Goſpell; with certaine conſiderations conduſing thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Delivered in a ſpeech</hi> BY IOHN PYM, Eſquire: Once a worthy Member of the Houſe of Commons, now deceaſed the eighth of <hi>December,</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>B. H.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>J. Weſt,</hi> neere the New-Exchange. 1643.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:126020:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:126020:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the Grievances of the Kingdome, delivered in <hi>Parliament,</hi> by <hi>Iohn Pym</hi> ESQUIER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ever Parliament had greater buſineſſes to <note place="margin">The prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of grievances will furth or the ſupply.</note> diſpatch, nor more difficulties to encounter; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee have reaſon to take all advantages of order and addreſſe, and hereby wee ſhall not only doe our owne worke, but diſpoſe and inable our ſelves for the better ſatisfaction of His Majeſties deſire of ſupply. The grievances being removed, our affections will carry us with ſpeed and cheerefulneſſe, to give His Majeſtie that which may be ſufficient both for his honour and ſupport. Thoſe that in firſt place ſhal endeavour to redreſſe the grievances, will be found not to hinder, but to be the furtherers of his Majeſties ſervice: hee that takes away weights, doth as much advantage motion, as hee that addeth wings.</p>
            <p>Diverſe pieces of this maine work have bin already propounded, <note place="margin">Great works are firſt to be conſidered in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell.</note> his endeavour ſhould bee to preſent to the Houſe a modell of the whole. In the Creation <hi>God</hi> made the world according to that <hi>Idea</hi> or form, which was eternally preexiſtent in the divine mind. <hi>Moſes</hi> was commanded to frame the Tabernacle after the patterne ſhewed him in the Mount. Thoſe actions are ſeldome well perfected in the execution, which are not firſt well moulded in the deſigne and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p>He ſaid, he would labour to contract thoſe manifold affaires both of the Church and State, which did ſo earneſtly require the wiſdom <note place="margin">A double method <hi>compounded</hi> of grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; cures.</note> and faithfulneſſe of this Houſe, into a double method of grievances and cures: and occauſe there wanted not ſome who pretended, that theſe things wherewith the Common-Wealth is now grieved, are mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h for the advantage of the King, and that the redreſſe of them will be to His Majeſties great diſadvantage and loſſe (hee ſaid) hee <note place="margin">Publike grievances diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to the King.</note> doubted not but to make it appeare, that in diſcovering the preſent g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat diſtempers and diſorders, and procuring remedy for them, we ſhould be no leſſe ſerviceable to his Majeſtie, who hath ſummoned us to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Councell, than uſefull to thoſe whom wee doe here
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:126020:3"/>
repreſent: for the better effecting whereof, he propounded three <note place="margin">The firſt generall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion.</note> maine branch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of his diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the firſt (hee ſaid) hee would offer them the ſeverall heads of ſome principall grievances, under which the Kingdome groaned.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the ſecond, he undertooke to prove, that the diſorders from whence thoſe grievances iſſued, were as hurtfull to the King as to the people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the third, he would adviſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch a way of healing and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thoſe grievances, as might be equally effectual to maintaine the honour and greatneſſe of the King, and to procure the proſperity and contentment of the people.</p>
            <p>In the handling whereof he promiſed to uſe ſuch expreſſions as <note place="margin">Sharp mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to bee mitigated in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. The K can do no wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</note> might mitigate the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rpenes and bitternes of thoſe things whereof he was to ſpeak, ſo far as his duty &amp; faithfulneſſe would allow. It is a great Prerogative to the K. and a great honour attributed to him in a Maxime of our Law, that he can doe no wrong, he is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Iuſtice, and if there be any injuſtice in the execution of his Commands, the Law caſts it upon the Miniſters, and frees the King. Activity, life, and vigour, are conveied into the ſublunary creatures, by the influence of Heaven: but the malignity and diſtemper, the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe of ſo many Epidemicall diſeaſes, do proceed from the noyſome vapours of the earth, or ſome ill affected qualities of the aire, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any infection or alteration of thoſe pure, celeſtiall and incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible bodies. In the like manner (he ſaid) the authority, the power and countenance of Princes may concurre in the actions of evill men, without partaking in the injuſtice and obliquitie of them. <note place="margin">Hurtfull projects pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the King under plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> Theſe matters where of we complaine, have bin preſented to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, either un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er the pretence of Royall Prerogatives, which he is bound to maintaine, or of publike good, which is the moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble object of Regall wiſdome. But the covetous and ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of others, have in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erpoſed betwixt his Royall intentions, and the happines of his people, making thoſe things pernicious and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which his Majeſtie apprehended as juſt, and profitable.</p>
            <p>He ſaid, the things which he was to propound, were of a various <note place="margin">A promiſe of modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> nature, many of them ſuch as required a very tender and exquiſite conſideration, In handling of which, as he would be bold to uſe the liberty of the place and relation wherein he ſtood, ſo hee would bee carefull to expreſſe that Modeſtie and humilitie, which might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by thoſe, of whoſe actions he was to ſpeake. And if his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <note place="margin">Submiſſion to reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> or his tongue ſhould ſlip into a particular miſtake, hee would not thinke it ſo great a ſhame, to faile by his owne weakneſſe, as hee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:126020:3"/>
ſhould eſteem it an honour and advantage, to be corrected by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of that houſe, to wc<hi rend="sup">h</hi> be ſubmitted himſelfe, with this proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he deſired no reformation ſo much as to reforme himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The greateſt liberty of the kingdom, is Religion;<note place="margin">Religion.</note> thereby we are freed from ſpiritual evils: and no impoſitions are ſo grievous, as thoſe that are laid upon the ſoule. The next great liberty, is Juſtice,<note place="margin">Iuſtice.</note> wherby we are preſerved from injurie in our perſons, and eſtates, from this is derived into the Common-wealth, peace, and order, and ſafety, and when this is interrupted, confuſion and danger are ready to over-whelme all. The third great liberty conſiſts in the power and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge <note place="margin">Priviledge of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> of Parliaments, this is the fountaine of law, the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the kingdom, the higheſt Court: this is inabled by the Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative and Conciliary power, to prevent evils to come; by the Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciary power, to ſuppreſſe and remove evils preſent. If you conſider theſe three great liberties in the order of dignitie, this laſt is inferiour to the other two, as meanes are inferour to the end; but if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them in the order of neceſſity, and uſe, this may juſtly claime the <note place="margin">The order propounded in handling theſe three great liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> firſt place, in our care, becauſe the end cannot be obtained without the means: if we do not preſerve this, we cannot long hope to enjoy either of the other. Therefore (he ſaid) being to ſpeak of thoſe grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances which lye upon the kingdome, he would obſerve this order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To mention thoſe, which were againſt the priviledge of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments.</item>
               <item>2. Thoſe which were prejudiciall to the Religion eſtabliſhed in the Kingdome.</item>
               <item>3. Thoſe which did interrupt the juſtice of the Realme, in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of our perſons, and propriety of our eſtates.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The priviledges of Parliament were not given for the ornament <note place="margin">The neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Parliament.</note> or advantage of thoſe, who are the members of Parliament, they have a reall uſe and efficacy, towards that which is the end of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: we are free from ſuits, that we may the more intirely addict our ſelves, to the publike ſervices: we have therfore liberty of ſpeech, that our Counſels may not bee corrupted with feare, or our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments perverted with ſelfe reſpects: thoſe three great faculties and functions of Parliament, the Legiſlative, Judiciary, and Conſiliary power, can not be well exerciſed without ſuch priviledges as theſe. The wiſdome of our Lawes, the faithfulneſſe of our Counſels, the righteouſneſſe of our judgments can hardly be kept pure and untain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if they proceed from diſtracted and reſtrained mindes.</p>
            <p>It is a good Rule of the Morall Philoſopher, <hi>Et non laedas mentem gubernatricem omnium actionum:</hi> Theſe powers of Parliament are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:126020:4"/>
to the body politike as the rationall faculties of the ſoule, to a man That which keepes all the parts of the Common-wealth in frame, and temper, ought to be moſt carefully preſerved in that freedome, vigour, and activity, which belongs to it ſelfe. Our predeceſſors in this houſe, have ever bin moſt carefull in the firſt place, to ſettle and ſecure their priviledges: and (he ſaid) he hoped that we having had greater breaches made upon us than heretofore, would bee no leſſe tender of them, and forward in ſeeking reparation for that which is paſt, and prevention of the like for the time to come.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Particular breaches of priviledge</note> Then he propounded diverſe particular points wherein the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Parliament had bin broken.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Reſtraint of ſpeech</note>Firſt, in reſtraiaing the members of the Houſe from ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Interdict of queſtions</note>Secondly, in forbidding the Speaker to put any Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Theſe two were practiſed the laſt day of the laſt Parliament (and, as was alledged, by his Majeſties command) and both of them trench upon the very life and being of Parliaments, for if ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining power as this ſhould take root, and be admitted, it will be impoſſible for us to bring any reſolution to perfection in ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as ſhall diſpleaſe thoſe about the King.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of members.</note> Thirdly, by impriſoning diverſe Members of the Houſe for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters done in Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iudiciall proceedings</note>Fourthly, by indictments, informations, and judgments in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary &amp; inferiour courts for ſpeeches &amp; proceedings in Parliaments</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Order to be bound in the good behaviour.</note>Fifthly, the diſgracefull order of the Kings Bench, whereby ſome members of this Houſe were injoyned to put in ſecurity of the good behaviour, and for refuſall thereof, they were continued in priſon, diverſe years, without any particular allegation againſt them: one of them was freed by death, others not diſmiſſed till his Majeſtie had declared his intention, to ſummon this Parliament. And this he noted not onely as a breach of priviledge, but as a violation of the common juſtice of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Sixthly by the ſudden and abrupt diſſolution of Parliaments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <note place="margin">Abrupt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </note> to the Law and cuſtome. It hath bin often declared in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that the Parliament ſhould not be diſſolved, till the petitions bee anſwered This (hee ſaid) was a great grievance, becauſe it doth prevent the redreſſe of other grievances. It were a hard caſe, that a private man ſhould bee put to death without being heard: As this repreſentative body of the Commons, receives a being by the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, ſo it receives a civill death by the diſſolution. Is it not a much more heavie doome, by which we loſe our being, and have this civill death inflicted on us, in diſpleaſure, and not to be allowed time and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:126020:4"/>
liberty to anſwer for our ſelves? that we ſhould not only dye, but have this marke of infamy laid upon us, to be made <hi>Inteſtabiles,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to make our wils, to diſpoſe of our buſines, as this Houſe hath alwayes uſed to do, before Adjournments or diſſolutions? yet this, hath often bin our caſe, we have not bin permitted to powre out our laſt ſighes and groanes, into the boſome of our deare Soveraigne; the words of dying men are full of piercing affections<hi>:</hi> if we might be heard to ſpeak, no doubt we ſhold ſo fully expreſſe our love, &amp; faith fulnes to our Prince, as might take off the falſe ſuggeſtions &amp; aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of others: at leaſt we ſhould in our humble ſupplications, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend ſome ſuch things to him in the name of his people as would make for his honour, and the publike good of his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thus he concluded the firſt ſort of grievances, being ſuch as were againſt the priviledge of Parliament, and paſſed on to the next, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion:<note place="margin">Grievances concerning Religion.</note> all which he conveyed under the foure heads.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</note>1 The firſt, was the great incouragement given to popery, of which he produced theſe particular evidences.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Suſpenſion of Lawes.</note>1 A ſuſpenſion of all Lawes againſt Papiſts, whereby they enjoy a free, and almoſt publike exerciſe of that Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gion, and thoſe good Statutes which were made for reſtraint of Idolatry, and ſuperſtition, are now a ground of ſecurity to them, in the practice of both, being uſed to no other end, but to get money into the Kings purſe: which as it is clearely againſt the intentions of the Law, ſo it is full of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe to the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>By this means a dangerous partie is cheriſhed, and increaſed, who are ready to cloſe with any opportunitie of diſturbing the peace and ſafety of the State. Yet (he ſaid) he did not deſire any new lawes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt popery, or any rigorous courſes in the execution of thoſe alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in force; he was far from ſeeking the ruine of their perſons or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, onely hee wiſht they might bee kept in ſuch a condition, as ſhould reſtraine them from doing hurt.</p>
            <p>It may be objected, there are moderate and diſcreet men amongſt <note place="margin">There can be no ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from papiſts.</note> them, men of eſtates, ſuch as have an intereſt in the peace and proſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perity of the Kingdome, as well as we. Theſe (he ſaid) were not to be conſidered according to their owne diſpoſition, but according to <note place="margin">but In their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability.</note> the nature of the body, whereof they are parties. The Planets have ſeverall and particular motions of their owne, yet they are all rapt and tranſported into a contrary courſe, by the ſuperior Orbe which comprehends them all. The Principles of Popery are ſuch, as are incompatible with any other RELIGION: there may bee a ſuſpenſion of violence, for ſome by reſpects,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:126020:5"/>
out the ultimate end, even of that moderation, is, that they may with more advantage extirpate that which is oppoſite to them. Laws will not reſtraine them, oaths will not, the Pope can diſpence with both theſe, and where there is occaſion, his command wil act them, to the diſturbance of the Realme, againſt their owne private diſpoſition, yea, againſt their own reaſon and judgment to obey him, to whom they have (eſpecially the Jeſuiticall party) abſolutely and intirely obliged themſelves, not only in ſpirituall matters, but in temporall, as they are in order <hi>ad Spiritualia. H.</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. and <hi>H.</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>France,</hi> were no Proteſtants themſelves, yet were murthered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they tolerated the Proteſtants, by which and many other preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents it appeares, that the King, that the Kingdome can have no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity but in their weakneſſe and diſabilitie to doe hurt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Admiſſion into places of power.</note> 2 A 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. incouragement is, their admiſſion into places of power and truſt in the Common-wealth, whereby they get many depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants and adherents, not only of their own, but even of ſuch as make profeſſion to be proteſtants.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Free reſort to London &amp; the court</note> 3 A third, their freedome of reſorting to <hi>London,</hi> and the Court, whereby they have opportunity, not only of Communicating their Counſels, and deſignes one to another, but of diving into his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Counſels, by the frequent acceſſe of thoſe who are active men, amongſt them, to the tables and company of great men, and under ſubtile pretences and diſguiſes, they want not meanes of cheriſhing their owne projects, and of indeavouring to mould and biaſſe the publike affaires to the great advantage of that partie.</p>
            <p n="4">4 A 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, that as they have a Congregation of Cardinals at <hi>Rome,</hi> to conſider of the apteſt wayes and means of eſtabliſhing the Popes authority and Religion in <hi>England:</hi> ſo they have a Nuncio here, to act and diſpoſe that party to the execution of thoſe Counſels, and by the aſſiſtance of ſuch cunning and Jeſuiticall ſpirits as ſwarm in this towne, to order and mannage all actions, and events, to the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of that maine end.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Innovations in matters of Religion</note> 2 The ſecond grievance in Religion, was from thoſe manifold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations lately introduced into ſeverall parts of the Kingdome, all inclining to Popery, and diſpoſing and ſitting men to entertaine it: the particulars are theſe. </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh tenets.</note>1 Divers of the chiefeſt points of Religion in difference betwixt us and the Papiſts have bin publikely defended in licenſed Books, in Sermons, in Vniverſity acts and diſputations.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Practice of popiſh cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> 2 Diverſe Popiſh Ceremonies have bin not only practiſed, but countenanced, yea little leſſe than injoyned, as Altars, Images, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixes,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:126020:5"/>
bowings, and other geſtures and obſervances, which put upon our Churches a ſhape and face of popery. He compared this to the dry bones in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> firſt they came together, then the ſinewes and the fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h came upon them, after this the skin covered them, and then breath and life was put into them: ſo (he ſaid) after theſe men had moulded us into an outward forme and viſage of popery, they would more boldly endeavour to breath into us the ſpirit &amp; life of popery.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Preferment of men po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Diſcourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of true profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. Inlargment of differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among our ſelves.</note> 3 The third grievance, was the countenancing and preferring thoſe men, who were moſt forward in ſetting up ſuch Innovations, the particul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs were ſo well knowne, that they needed not to be named.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Diſcourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of true profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</note>4 The fourth was, the diſcouragement of thoſe who were known to be moſt conſcionable, and faithfull profeſſors of the truth: ſome of the wayes of effecting this, he obſerved to be theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Inlargment of differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among our ſelves.</note>1 The courſes taken to inforce and inlarge thoſe unhappy differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for matters of ſmall moment, which have bin amongſt our ſelves, and to raiſe up new occaſions of further diviſion, wherby many have bin induced to forſake the land, not ſeeing the end of thoſe volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and humane Injunctions in things appertaining to <hi>Gods</hi> worſhip: whereas thoſe who are indeed lovers of Religion, and of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God, would ſeeke to make up thoſe breaches, and to unite us more entirely againſt the common enemy.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Over rigid proſceution of the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous for things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</note> 2 The over rigid proſecution of thoſe who are ſcrupulous in uſing ſome things enjoyned, which are held by thoſe who enjoyn them, to be in themſelves indifferent. It hath bin ever the deſire of this Houſe, expreſt in many Parliaments in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time and ſince, that ſuch might be tenderly uſed. It was one of our petitions delivered at <hi>Oxford</hi> to his Majeſtie that now is: but what little moderation it hath produced, is not unknowne to us all, any other vice almoſt <note place="margin">Vnjuſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments for matters not by law. </note> may be better indured in a Miniſter than Inconformitie.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The unjuſt puniſhments, and vexations of ſundry perſons for matters required, without any warrant of Law: as</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reading the Booke.</note> For not reading the book concerning recreation on the Lords day.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Table ſet Altar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. </note>For not removing the Communion Table to bee ſet Altarwiſe at the Eaſt end of the Chancell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Comming to the railes </note>For not comming up to the Railes to receive the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preaching upon the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds day. </note>For preaching the Lords day in the afternoone.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Varying from the catechiſme. </note>For Catechiſing in any other words and manner than in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe words of the ſhort catechiſme in the Common Prayer booke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Abuſe of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</note>The fifth and laſt grievance concerning Religion, was the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>croachment and abuſe of Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction: the particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lars mentioned are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:126020:6"/>
               <note place="margin">In fining &amp; impriſoning </note>1 Fining and impriſoning in caſes not allowed by Law. </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Claiming juriſdiction to be <hi>Iure Divino.</hi> 
               </note>2 Their challenging their juriſdiction to be appropriate to their order, which they alledge to be <hi>jure Divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Articles of the Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</note>3 The contriving and publiſhing of new articles, upon which they inforce the Churchwardens to take oathes, and to make inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and preſentments, as if ſuch articles had the force of Canons: and this, he ſaid, was an effect of great preſumption and boldneſſe, not only in the Biſhops, but in their Archdeacons, Officials and Chancellors, taking upon themſelves a kind of Synodall authority: and the Injunctions of this kinde, might well partake in name with that part of the common Law, which is called the Extravagants.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Grievances concerning the liberty of perſons and eſtates.</note> Having diſpatcht theſe ſeverall points, hee proceeded to the third part of grievances, being ſuch as are againſt the common juſtice of the Realm, in the liberties of our perſons, and proprietie of our eſtates, of which (he ſaid) he had many to propound: In doing whereof, he would rather obſerve the order of time, wherein they were acted, than of conſequence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but when hee ſhould come to the cure, hee ſhould then perſwade the Houſe to begin with thoſe, who were of moſt importance, as being now in execution, and very much preſſing and exhauſting the Common-Wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tonnage &amp; poundage impoſitions</note> He began with the Tonnage and poundage, and other impoſitions not warranted by Law: and becauſe theſe burdens had long lyen upon us, and the principles which produced them, are the ſame from whence diverſe others are derived, he thought it neceſſary to premiſe a ſhort narrative, and relation of the grounds and proceed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs of the power of impoſing herein practiſed. It was (he ſaid) a fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall <note place="margin">Not to be taken but by conſent in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </note> truth eſſentiall to the conſtitution and government o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, an hereditary liberty and priviledge of all the free borne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Land, that no tax, tallage, or oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r charge might be laid upon us, without common conſent in Parliament, this was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the Conqueror,<note place="margin">Acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledged by the <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> 
               </note> ratified in that contract which hee made with this Nation, upon his admittance to the Kingdome, declared and confirmed in the Lawes which he publiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sometimes broken by other Kings but never denyed </note>This hath never bin denyed to any of our Kings, though broken and interrupted by ſome of them, eſpecially by K. <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. then againe confirmed by <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> and other ſucceeding lawes: yet not ſo well ſetled, but that it was ſometime attempted by the two ſucceeding <hi>Edwards,</hi> in whoſe times the ſubjects wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very ſenſible of all the breaches made upon the common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ibertie, and by the opportunitie of frequent Parliaments, purſued them with freſh complaints, and for the moſt part, found redreſſe,<note place="margin">Thoſe brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceeding <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liaments</hi>
               </note> and procured the right of the ſubject to be fortfied by new Statutes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:126020:6"/>
He obſerved that thoſe Kings, even in the Acts whereby they did <note place="margin">Some mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for the ſubject in theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry breaches.</note> break the Law, did really affirme the ſubjects liberty, and diſclaime that right of impoſing, which is now chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, for they did uſually procure the Merchants conſent, to ſuch taxes as were laid, therby to put a colour of juſtice upon their proceeding, and ordinarily they were limited to a ſhort time, and then propounded to the ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> where they were cancell'd or confirmed, as the neceſſity and ſtate of the Kingdome did require.</p>
            <p>But for the moſt part, ſuch charges upon merchandize, were taken <note place="margin">The grant by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment moſt uſuall.</note> by authority of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and granted for ſome ſhort time, in a greater or leſſer proportion, as was requiſite for ſupply of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like occaſions, 6 or 12 in the pound, for one, two, or three yeers, as they ſaw cauſe, to be imployed for the defence of the Sea, and it was acknowledged ſo clearly, to be in the power of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that they <note place="margin">At firſt vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of time and perſons </note> have ſometimes bin granted to Noble men, ſometimes to Merchants to be diſpoſed for that uſe. Afterward they were granted to the King for life,<note place="margin">Afterwards Confirmed to the King for life. </note> and ſo continued for divers deſcents, yet ſtill as a gift and grant of the Commons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No contrary practiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Ed. 3 and Q Mary </note>Betwixt the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> the third, and Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> never Prince (that he could remember) offered to demand any impoſition, but by gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in <hi>Parliament:</hi> Q. <hi>Mary</hi> laid a charge upon cloth, by the equity of the Statute of Tunnage &amp; Poundage, becauſe the rate ſet upon wool was much more than upon cloth, &amp; there being little wool carried out of the Kingdom unwrought, the Q thought ſhe had reaſon, to lay ſomwhat more, yet not ful ſo much, as brought them to an equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,<note place="margin">Pretended equity for the Cuſtome upon cloth.</note> but that there ſtil continued a leſſe charge upon wool wrought <note place="margin">The grounds of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted Cuſtome.</note> into cloth, than upon wool carried out unwrought; until K. <hi>Jame</hi>'s times, when upon <hi>Nicholſons</hi> project, there was a further addition of charge, but ſtill upon pretence of the Statute, which is that we call the pretermitted cuſtome.</p>
            <p>In Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> time, one or two litle impoſitions crept in, the general <note place="margin">Bates Caſe.</note> proſperity of her raign overſhadowing ſmall errours and innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: one of theſe was upon Currans, by occaſion of the Merchants complaints, that the <hi>Venetians</hi> had laid a charge upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> cloth, that ſo we might be even with them, and force them the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to take it off: this being demanded by K. <hi>Iames,</hi> was denied <note place="margin">The judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in for the King.</note> by one <hi>Bates</hi> a Merchant, and upon a ſuit in the Exchequer, was adjudged for the King.</p>
            <p>The manner of which judgement was thus: There were then but three Iudges, in that Court, all differing from one another in the grounds of their ſentences. The firſt was of opinion, the King might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:126020:7"/>
impoſe upon ſuch commodities as were forraigne, and ſuperfluous <note place="margin">Reſulting from diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Iudges.</note> as Currans were, but not upon ſuch as were native, and to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported, or neceſſary, and to be imported for the uſe of the kingdom. The ſecond Iudge was of opinion, he might impoſe upon all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Merchandiſe, whether ſuperfluous or no, but not upon native. The third, that for as much as the King had the cuſtody of the Ports and the guard of the Seas, and that he might open and ſhut up the ports as he pleaſed, he had a prerogative to impoſe upon all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, both exported and imported.</p>
            <p>This ſingle, diſtracted &amp; divided judgement, is the foundation of <note place="margin">The only foundation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</note> all the impoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions now in practice<hi>:</hi> for after this, K. <hi>Iam</hi> laid new charges upon all commodities outward and inward, not limited to a certaine time, and occaſion, but reſerved to himſelfe, his heires and ſucceſſors for ever; the firſt, impoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions in fee ſimple, that were <note place="margin">followed with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and preſerved by breaches of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</note> ever heard of in this kingdome. This judgement, and the right of impoſing thereupon aſſumed was a queſtion in <hi>ſeptimo &amp; duodeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> of that King, and was the cauſe of the breach of both thoſe <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,</hi> In 18. and 21. <hi>Jacobi,</hi> it was declined by this Houſe, that they might preſerve the favour of the K. for the diſpatch of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great buſineſſes, upon w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they were more eſpecially attentive.</p>
            <p>In 1. of his Majeſty, It neceſſarily came to be remembred upon the <note place="margin">The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without diminution of the Kings profit.</note> propoſition on the Kings part, for renewing the bill of Tonnage and Poundage, but ſo moderate was that <hi>Parliament,</hi> that they thought rather to confirme the impoſitions already ſet by a law to be made, than to aboliſh them by a judgement in <hi>Parliament,</hi> but that and divers inſuing <hi>Parliaments</hi> have been unhappily broken, before that endeavour could be accompliſhed, only at the laſt mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, a Remonſtrance was made concerning the liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, in this point, and it hath alwayes been expreſt to be the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Houſe, and ſo it was (as hee ſaid) his owne mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the propoſition now made, to ſettle and reſtore the right according to law, and not to diminiſh the Kings profit, but to eſtabliſh it by a free grant in <hi>Parliament.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">New bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ſince the laſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Since the breach of the laſt <hi>Parliament,</hi> his Majeſty hath by a new book of Rates very much increaſed the burden upon Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, and now Tonnage and Poundage, old and new impoſitions are all taken by Prerogative, without any grant in <hi>Parliament,</hi> or <note place="margin">Divers miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes from theſe grievances. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom bound by one pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate caſe:</note> authority of law, as we conceive, from whence divers inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and miſchiefes are produced.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The danger of the preſident, that a judgement in one Court, and in one caſe, is made binding to all the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:126020:7"/>
2 Mens goods are ſeized, their legall ſuits are ſtopped, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <note place="margin">Interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</note> denied to thoſe, that deſire to take the benefit of the Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The great ſummes of money received upon theſe impoſitioins, <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſimploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſummes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</note> intended for the guard of the Seas, claimed and defended upon no ground, but of publike truſt, for protection of Merchants and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the ports, are diſperſed to other uſes, and a new taxe raiſed for the ſame purpoſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Theſe burdens are ſo exceſſive, that trade is thereby very much <note place="margin">The bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive.</note> hindered, the commodities of our owne, groweth extreamly aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and thoſe imported much inhaunſed, all which lies not upon the Merchant alone, but upon the generality of the ſubject, and by this meanes the ſtocke of the Kingdom is much diminiſht, our exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being leſſe profitable, and our importation more chargeable. And if the warres and troubles in the neighbour parts had not brought almoſt the whole ſtreame of Trade into this Kingdom, we ſhould have found many more prejudicial effects of thoſe impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, long before this time, than yet we have done; eſpecially they <note place="margin">To the Ame<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rican plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall.</note> have been inſupportable to the poore plantations, whither many of his Majeſties ſubjects have been transported, in divers parts of the Continent, and Iſlands of <hi>America,</hi> being a deſigne tending to the honour of the Kingdome, and the inlargement of his Majeſties do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions: The adventurers in this noble worke, have for the moſt part, no other ſupport but Tobacco, upon which, ſuch a heavy rate is ſet, that the King receives twice as much, as the true value of the commoditie to the owner.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whereas theſe great burdens have cauſed divers Merchants <note place="margin">Impoſitions upon trade intercour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory.</note> to apply themſelves to a way of traffique abroad by tranſporting goods from one Country to another, without bringing them home into <hi>England</hi> It hath been lately endeavoured to ſet an Impoſition upon this trade: ſo as the King will have a duty out of thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities which never came within his dominions, to the great diſcouragement of ſuch active and induſtrious men.</p>
            <p>The next generall head of Civil grievances, was inforcing men <note place="margin">Compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Knighthood</note> to compound for Knighthood, which though it may ſeeme paſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is divers years ſince it was uſed, yet upon the ſame grounds the King may renew it, as often as he pleaſeth, for the compoſition lookes backward, and the offence continuing, is ſubiect to a new fine. The ſtate of that buſineſſe, he layed downe thus.</p>
            <p>Heretofore when the ſervices due by tenure, were taken in kind <note place="margin">The Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ground of the charg</note> it were fit there ſhould be ſome way of tryall, and approbation of thoſe, that were bound to ſuch ſervices. Therefore it was ordained,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:126020:8"/>
that ſuch as were to do Knights ſervice, after they came of age, and had poſſeſſion of their lands, and ſhould be made Knights, that is, publikely declared, to be fit for that ſervice, divers ceremonies and ſolemnities were in uſe for this purpoſe; and if by the parties neglect this was not done, he was puniſhable by Fine: there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thoſe times an ordinary and open way to get Knighthood, for theſe who were borne to it.</p>
            <p>Although the uſe of this hath for divers ages been diſcontinued, yet there have paſt very few Kings, under whom there hath not bin <note place="margin">An old grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance in the kind.</note> a general Summons, requiring thoſe who had lands of ſuch value as the Law preſcribes, to appeare at the Coronation, or ſome other great ſolemnity, and to be Knighted, and yet nothing intended but <note place="margin">New in the manner and exceſſe,</note> the getting of ſome ſmall fines: ſo as this grievance is not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new in the kind, though it be new in the manner, and in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of it, and that in divers reſpects.</p>
            <p>1 Firſt, It hath been extended beyond all intention of and colour of law, not only Inne-holders, but likewiſe Leaſe-holders, Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, Merchants and others, ſcarce any man free from it. <note place="margin">Reſpect of</note>
            </p>
            <p>2 The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es have beene immoderate, far beyond the proportion, <note place="margin">The genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> of former times.</p>
            <p>3 The proceedings have been without any example, preſident, or rule of juſtice: for though thoſe that were ſummoned did appeare, <note place="margin">Greatneſſe of fines. Multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes and iſſues.</note> yet diſtreſſes infinite were made out againſt them; and iſſues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed and multiplied, and no way open to diſcharge thoſe iſſues, by plea or otherwiſe, but only by compounding with the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners at their own pleaſure.</p>
            <p>3 The third was, the great Inundation of Monopolies, whereby heavy burthens are laid, not only upon forraigne, but alſo native <note place="margin">Monopolies introduced by the ſope pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by papiſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> commodities. Theſe began in the Sope-Patent; the principall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers in this, were div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs popiſh Recuſants, men of eſtate and quality, ſuch as in likelyhood did not only aime at their private gaine, but that by this open breach of Law, the King and his people might be more fully divided, &amp; the wayes of <hi>Parliament</hi> men more throughly obſtructed. Amongſt the infinite inconveniences and <note place="margin">Full of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife.</note> miſchiefes which this did produce, theſe few may be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The impairing the goodneſſe, and inhancing the price of moſt <note place="margin">1 the price of commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſt and goodneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, Reſtraint of trade.</note> of the Commodities and Manufactures of the Realme, yea of thoſe, who are of moſt neceſſary and common uſe, as Salt, Sope, Beere, Coles, and infinite others.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That under colour of Licences, Trades, and Manufactures are reſtrained to a few hands, and many of the Subjects deprived of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:126020:8"/>
their ordinary way of livelyhood.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That upon ſuch illegal grants, a great number of perſons had bin unjuſtly vexed by Purſevants, Impriſonments attendance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Illegall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments &amp; vexations </note> the Councell Table, ſeiſure of goods, and many other wayes.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Shipmony.</note>4 The fourth, that great and unparalleld grievance of the Shipmoney, which though it may ſeeme to have more warrant of Law than the reſt, becauſe there hath a judgement paſt for it, yet in truth it is thereby aggravated, if it be conſidered, that <note place="margin">Aggravated not ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Iudgement. Which is not grounded upon any law cuſtom preſident or authority of law bookes.</note> that judgement is founded upon the naked opinion of ſome judges, without any written Law, without any cuſtome, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Law broken, yea without any one preſident for it. Many expreſſe Laws, many Declarations in <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and the conſtant judgment and practiſe of all times being againſt it, yea in the nature of it, it will be found to be diſproportionable to the caſe of neceſſity which is pretended to be the ground of it.</p>
            <p>Neceſſity excludes all formalities and ſolemnities, it is no <note place="margin">The courſe unproper for a caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</note> time then to make Levies and Taxes to build and prepare Ships, every mans perſon, every mans Ships are to be imployed for the reſiſting of an invading enemy: the right on the Subjects part was ſo cleare, and the pretences againſt it ſo weake, that hee thought no man would venture his reputation or conſcience in the defence of that judgment, being ſo contrary to the grounds of the Law, to the practiſe of former times, and ſo inconſiſtent <note place="margin">Abounding in variety of miſchiefes.</note> in it ſelfe. Amongſt many inconveniences and obloquies of this grievance he noted theſe.</p>
            <p>1 That it extendeth to all perſons, and to all times, it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected <note place="margin">The general extent and remedileſſe condition,</note> our goods to diſtreſſe, and our perſons to impriſonment, and the cauſes of it being ſecret and inviſible, referred to his Majeſties breſt alone, the Subject was left without poſſibility of exception, and reliefe.</p>
            <p>2 That there was no rules or limits for the proportion, ſo that <note place="margin">Arbitrary proportion.</note> no man knew what eſtate he had, or how to order his courſe or expences.</p>
            <p>3 That it was taken out of the Subjects purſe, by a writ, and <note place="margin">Impoſed by writ diſpoſ'd by inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> brought into the Kings Coffers by inſtructions from the Lords of his moſt honourable privy Councell. In the legall defence of it, the Writ only did appeare; of the inſtructions, there was no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice taken, which yet in the reall execution of it, were moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant. It carryes the face of ſervice in the Writ, and of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue in the inſtructions<hi>:</hi> if this way had not been found to turn the Ship, into money, it would eaſily have appeared how incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:126020:9"/>
this ſervice is with the office of a Sheriffe, in the inland <note place="margin">Improper for the Sheriffes.</note> Counties, and how incongruous and inconvenient for the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants. The law in a body politike is of like nature, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes prepareth and diſpoſeth proper and fit inſtruments and <note place="margin">Vnprovided for by law.</note> Organs, for every naturall operation; if the Law had intended any ſuch charge as this, there ſhould have beene certaine rules, ſuitable meanes and courſes, for the levying and managing of it.</p>
            <p>5 The fift was the Inlargement of the Forreſts beyond the <note place="margin">Inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Forreſts.</note> bounds and perambulations appointed and ſtabliſhed by act of Parliament, twenty ſeven and twenty eight <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>firſt,</hi> and that this is done upon the ſame reaſons and exceptions <note place="margin">Againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutes.</note> which had beene on the Kings part propounded, and by the Commons anſwered in Parliament, not long after that eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment. It is not unknowne to many in this Houſe, that thoſe perambulations were the fruit and effect of that famous Charter, which is called <hi>Charta de forreſta,</hi> whereby many tumults, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, <note place="margin">Charta de forreſta, made uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</note> and diſcontents had beene taken away, and compoſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and his ſubjects, &amp; it is ful of danger, that by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving thoſe old Queſtions we may fal into the like diſtſtempers.</p>
            <p>He ſaid, that hereby no blame could fall upon that great Lord <note place="margin">Iuſtice in Eyer clered</note> who is now Iuſtice of Eyre, and in whoſe name theſe things were acted, it ſhould not be expected that he ſhould take notice of the lawes and cuſtomes of the realme, therefore he was careful <note place="margin">The Anſwer lies upon the Iudges.</note> to procure the aſſiſtance and direction of the Iudges, and if any thing were done againſt law, it was for them to anſwer, and not for him.</p>
            <p>The particular irregularities and obliquities of this buſineſſe <note place="margin">Particular obliquities.</note> were theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The ſurreptitious procuring a verdict for the King, without <note place="margin">Surreptiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous procee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dings.</note> giving notice to the Countrey, whereby they might be prepared to give in evidence for their owne intereſt and indemnity; as was done in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Whereas the Iudges in the Iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice ſeat in <hi>Eſsex</hi> were conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">A judgment pretended.</note> with, about the entry of the former verdict, and delivered their opinion touching that alone, without medling with the point of right, this opinion was after inforced in other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as if it had beene a judgement upon the matter, and the Councell for the Countie diſcountenanced in ſpeaking, becauſe it was ſaid to be already adjudged.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The inheritance of divers of the Subjects have been hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</note> diſturbed after the quiet poſſeſſion of three or foure hundred
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:126020:9"/>
yeares, and a way open for the diſturbance of many others.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Great ſums of mony have bin drawn from ſuch as have lands <note place="margin">Inforced to compound for great fines.</note> within theſe pretended bounds, and thoſe who have forborne to make compoſition, have beene threatned with the execution of the forreſt lawes.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The fifth, was the ſelling of Nuſances, or at leaſt, ſome ſuch <note place="margin">Selling of Nuſances.</note> things as are ſuppoſed to be Nuſances.</p>
            <p>The King as Father of the Common wealth is to take care of <note place="margin">The legall tryal of Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſances o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,</note> the publik commodities, &amp; advantages of his ſubjects, as Rivers, Highways, Common Sewers, &amp; ſuch like, &amp; is to remove what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is prejudiciall to them, &amp; for the tryall of thoſe, there are legall and ordinary writs, of <hi>Ad quod damnum:</hi> but of late a new <note place="margin">A new ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trajudiciall way practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</note> and extrajudiciall way hath been taken of declaring matters to be Nuſances, and divers have thereupon been queſtioned, and if they would not compound they have been fined; if they do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, that which was firſt proſecuted as a common Nuſance, is taken into the Kings protection, and allowed to ſtand, &amp; having <note place="margin">Compoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and</note> yeelded the King Mony, no further care is taken, whether it bee good or bad for the common wealth By this a very great &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like truſt is either broken or abuſed: if the matter compounded <note place="margin">A publike truſt broken or abuſed.</note> for be truly a Nuſance, then it is broken to the hurt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: if it bee not a Nuſance, then is it abuſed to the hurt of the party, the particulars mentioned, were:</p>
            <p>1 The Commiſſion for buildings in &amp; about this town, which <note place="margin">The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</note> heretofore hath bin preſented by this Houſe as a grievance in K. <hi>Iames</hi> his time, but now of late the execution hath beene much <note place="margin">Commiſſion for bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lding</note> more frequent and prejudiciall than it was before.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Commiſſion for Depopulations, which began <note place="margin">Depopula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> ſome few yearers ſince, and is ſtill in hot proſecution.</p>
            <p>By both theſe, the ſubject is reſtrained from diſpoſing of his <note place="margin">The ſeveral miſchiefes of both.</note> owne, ſome have been commanded to demoliſh their houſes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have been forbidden to build, other after great trouble and vexation, have been forced to redeeme their peace with large ſummes, and they ſtill emaine by law, as lyable to a new queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion as before, for it is agreed by all, that the King cannot licence a common Nuſance: and although in deed theſe are not ſuch, yet it is a matter of very ill conſequence, that under that name they ſhould be compounded for, and may in ill times be made a preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for the Kings of this Realme to claime a power of licencing ſuch things as are Nuſances indeed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:126020:10"/>
The ſeventh, the Military charges laid upon the ſeverall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <note place="margin">Military charges</note> of the Kingdom, ſometimes by warrant under his Majeſties ſignature, ſometimes by Letters from the Councel Table, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (ſuch hath been the boldnes and preſumption of ſome men) by the order of the Lord <hi>Lievtenants,</hi> or deputy Leivtenant alone.</p>
            <p>This is a growing evill ſtill multiplying and increaſing from a few particulars to many from ſmall ſummes to great: it began <note place="margin">A growing evill. </note> firſt to be practiſed as a loane, for ſupply of coat and conduct mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,<note place="margin">Coat and conduct mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> practiſed by Q Eliz.</note> &amp; for this it hath ſome countenance, from the uſe in Q <hi>Eliz.</hi> time, when the Lords of the Councell did often deſire the deputy Lievtenants to procure ſo much mony to be laid out in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try as the ſervice did require, with a promiſe to pay it againe in <hi>London;</hi> for which purpoſe there was a conſtant warrant in the Exchequer. This (he ſaid) was the practice in her time, and in a great part of K <hi>James,</hi> and the payments ſo certain, as it was lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle otherwiſe, than taking up mony upon bils of exchange; at this day they follow theſe preſidents, in the manner of the demand (for it is with a promiſe of a repayment) but not in the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and readines of ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>The firſt particular brought into a tax (as he thought) was the <note place="margin">Muſter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters wages,</note> Muſter Maſters wages, at which many repined, but being for ſmall ſummes, it began to be generally digeſted: yet in the laſt <hi>Parliament,</hi> this Houſe was ſenſible of it, and to avoyd the danger of the preſident that the Subjects ſhould bee forced to make any payments without conſent in <hi>Parliament,</hi> they thought upon a Bill that may bee a rule to the Lieutenants what to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and to the People what to pay. But the hopes of this Bill were daſht in the diſſolution of that <hi>Parliament.</hi> Now of late divers other particulars are growing into practice, which make the grievance much more heavy: thoſe mentioned were theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing,</note> 1 Preſſing men againſt their will, and forcing them which are rich or unwilling to ſerve to find others in their place.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">Publike ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazins,</note> 2 The proviſion of publike Magazins for powder, and other Munition, Spades and Pickaxes.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">Salary of officers</note>3 The Salary of Divers officers beſides the Muſter-Maſter. </item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin"> Cart horſes and Carts,</note>4 The buying of Cart-horſes and Carts, and hyring of Carts for Cariages.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Extrajudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</note> The eighth, the extrajudiciall declarations of Judges whereby the ſubjects have beene bound in matters of great importance without hearing of Counſell or Argument on their part, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:126020:10"/>
are left without legall remedie, by writ of errour or otherwiſe: he remembred the expreſſion uſed by another member of the Houſe of a teeming Parliament: this (hee ſaid) was a teeming grievance: from hence have iſſued moſt of the great grievances now in being, <note place="margin">A teeming grievance.</note> The Shipmoney, the pretended Nuſances already mentioned, and ſome others which have not yet beene toucht upon: Eſpecially that concerning the proceedings of Eccleſiaſticall Courts.</p>
            <p>The ninth, That the authority and wiſdom of the Councell Table, <note place="margin">Monopolies countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Councell Table. The ancient oath of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours.</note> have bin applyed to the contriving and managing of ſeverall Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies, and other great grievances (he ſaid) The inſtitution of the Councell Table, was much for the advantage and ſecurity of the ſubject, to avoyd ſurreptions and precipitate Courts in the great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Kingdome: That by Law an oath is to be taken by all thoſe of the Kings Counſell, in which amongſt other things it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, that they ſhould for no cauſe forbeare to doe right, to all the Kings people, and if ſuch an oath be not now taken, he wiſht it might be brought into uſe againe.</p>
            <p>It was the honour of that Table, to bee as it were incorporated <note place="margin">Their truſt &amp; dignity.</note> with the King, His royall power and greatneſſe did ſhine moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſly in their actions, and in their Counſels: We have heard of Projectors and Reſurees here tofore and what opinion and reliſh they have found in this Houſe is not unknowne. But that any ſuch thing ſhould bee acted by the Councell Table, which might give ſtrength and countenance to Monopolies, as it hath not beene uſed till now of late, ſo it cannot be apprehended without the juſt griefe of the honeſt ſubject, and incouragement of thoſe who are ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
            <p>He remembred that in <hi>Tortio</hi> of King.</p>
            <p>A Noble Gentleman, then a very worthy member of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons <note place="margin">Much dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and debaſed.</note> Houſe, now a Great Lord and eminent Councellour of State, did in this place declare this opinion concerning that clauſe uſed to bee inſerted in Pattents of Monopoly, whereby Iuſtices of Peace are commanded to aſſiſt the Pattentees, this he urged as a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to thoſe Gentlemen, which are in Commiſſion to bee ſo meanely imployed, with much more reaſon, may we in jealouſie of the honour of the Councell Table, humbly deſire that their precious <note place="margin">By being imployed in matters of ſuch ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</note> time, their great abilities deſigned to the publike care and ſervice of the Kingdome, may not receive ſuch a ſtaine, ſuch a diminution, as to be imployed in matters of ſo ill report, in the eſtimation of the law: of ſo ill effect, in the apprehenſion of the people. <note place="margin">Star cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a great Councell.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The tenth, The High Court of Starchamber, which ſome think,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:126020:11"/>
ſucceed that, which in the Parliament Rolles is called, <hi>Magnum Concilium,</hi> and to which, Parliaments were wont ſo often to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre thoſe important matters, which they had no time to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. This Court which in the late reſtauration or erection of it, <note place="margin">A court e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</note> in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh's time, was eſpecially deſigned to reſtraine the oppreſſion of great men, and to remove the obſtructions and impediments of the Law. This which is both a Court of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and a Court of Juſtice, hath beene made an inſtrument of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting and defending Monopolies and other grievances; to ſet a face of right upon theſe things, which are unlawfull in their owne nature: a face of publike good, upon ſuch as are pernicious in their uſe and execution. The Soape-Patent, and diverſe other <note place="margin">Applyed the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of Monopolies</note> evidences thereof may be given, ſo well knowne, as not to require a particular relation: And as if this were not enough, this Court ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h lately intermedled with the Ship-money, diverſe Sheriffes have beene queſtioned, for not levying, and collecting ſuch ſums, as their Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nties have beene charged with, and if this beginning be not prevented, the Star-Chamber will become a Court of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and it ſhall be made crime not to collect or pay ſuch taxes, as <note place="margin">To the reco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>very of ſhip money.</note> the State ſhall require.</p>
            <p>The Eleventh, He ſaid, he was gone very high, yet hee muſt <note place="margin">The Kings ediccts and Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> goe a little higher: that great and moſt eminent power of the King of making Edicts and Proclamations, which are ſaid to bee <hi>Leges Temporis,</hi> with whom our Princes have uſed to encounter with ſudden and unexpected danger, as would not indure ſo much delay, as aſſembling the great Councell of the Kingdome, This which is one of the moſt Glorious beames of Majeſtie, rigorous in commanding Reverence, and ſubjection, to our unſpeakeable <note place="margin">For the ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nopolies.</note> griefe, hath been often exerciſed for the enjoyning and maintaining ſundry Monopolies, and other grants, exceeding burdenſome, and prejudiciall to the people.</p>
            <p>The Twelfth, Although hee was come as high as he could up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">The word and truth of God.</note> earth, yet the preſumption of evill men did leade him one ſtep higher, even as high as Heaven, as high as the Throne of God. It was now, hee ſaid, growne common, for ambitious and corrupt men of the Clergie, to abuſe the truth of God, and the bond of Conſcience, preaching downe the Lawes and liberties of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, pretending Divine authority, for an abſolute power in the King, to doe what he would with our perſons, and goods, this hath <note place="margin">Pretended for the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Kings.</note> been often publiſhed in Sermons, and Printed books, and is now the high way to preferment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:126020:11"/>
The laſt Parliament, we had a ſentence for an offence of this kinde, againſt one <hi>Mannering,</hi> then a Doctor, now a Biſhop, concerning whom (hee ſaid) hee would ſay no more but this, that when he ſaw him at his Barre, in the moſt humble dejected poſture, <note place="margin">The offence of D. <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nering.</hi>
               </note> that ever hee obſerved, hee thought hee would not ſo ſoone have leapt into a Biſhops Chaire, but his ſucceſſe hath emboldened o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, therefore (hee ſaid) this may well bee noted as a double <note place="margin">Now practi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. To the great hurt and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the people.</note> gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>evance, that ſuch doctrine ſhould bee allowed, that ſuch men ſhould be preferred, yea as a roote of grievances whereby they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to corrupt the Kings Conſcience, and as much as in them lyes, to deprive the people of that Royall protection, to which his Majeſtie is bound by the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdom, and his own perſonall Oath.</p>
            <p>The thirteenth: The long intermiſſion of the Parliaments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <note place="margin">The Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of <hi>Parliaments</hi>
               </note> to the two ſtatutes yet in force, whereby it is appointed there ſhould bee Parliaments once a yeare, at the leaſt, and moſt contrary to the publike good of the Kingdome, for this being well remedied would produce remedies for all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Having put through the ſeverall heads of grievances, hee came <note place="margin">The ſubjects grievances hurtfull to the King.</note> to the ſecond maine branch, propounded in the beginning. That the diſorders from whence theſe grievances iſſued, were as hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the King, as to the people, of which hee gave diverſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The interruption of the ſweet communion which ought to <note place="margin">B. interrupt their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note> bee betwixt the King and His People, in matters of grace and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</p>
            <p>They have need of him by His generall pardon, to bee ſecured from projectors, and informers, to bee freed from obſolete Lawes, from the ſubtle devices of ſuch as ſeeke to reſtraine the Prerogative to their own private advantage, and the publike hurt; and he hath need of them for counſell and ſupport, in great and extraordinary occaſions. This mutuall entercourſe would ſo weane the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and intereſts of His Subjects, into his actions and deſignes, that their wealth and their perſons would bee his, his owne eſtate would bee managed to moſt advantage, and publike undertakings would bee proſecuted at the charge and adventure of the Subject: The Victorious attempts in Queene <hi>ELIZABETHS</hi> time upon <hi>Portugall, Spaine,</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> were for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part, made upon the poore Subjects purſes, and not upon the Queenes, though the Honour and profit of the ſucceſſe, did moſt accrew to her.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:126020:12"/>
2 Thoſe often breaches and diſcontentments betwixt the King <note place="margin">By dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents.</note> and the people, are very apt to diminiſh his reputation abroad, and diſadvantage his treaties and alliances.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The apprehenſion of the favour and incouragement given to <note place="margin">By weakn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie abroad.</note> Popery, hath much weakned his Majeſties party beyond the Sea, and impared that advantage which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and His Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Father hath heretofore made, of being hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the Proteſtant union.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The innovations in Religion and rigour of Eccleſiaſticall <note place="margin">By forcing his ſubjects to leave the kingdome.</note> Courts, have forced a great many of his Majeſties Subjects to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Land, whereby not only their perſons, and their poſterity, but their wealth, and their induſtry are loſt to this Kingdome, much to the demoliſhing of His Majeſties Cuſtomes and Subſidies. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other inconveniences, this was eſpecially to bee obſerved, that diverſe Clothiers driven out of the Countrey, had ſet up the manufacture of Cloth beyond the Seas, whereby this State is like to ſuffer much by abatement of the price of Woolls, and by want of imployment for the poore, both which likewiſe tend to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties particular loſſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It puts the King upon unproper wayes of ſupply, which being <note place="margin">By unpro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per wayes of ſupply.</note> not warranted by Law, are much more burdenſome to the ſubject, than advantagious to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Majeſty. In <hi>France</hi> not long ſince, upon a ſurvey of the Kings Revenue, it was found that two parts in three, never came to the Kings purſe, but were diverted to the profit of the officers or Miniſters of the Crowne, and it was thought a very good ſervice and reformation, to reduce two parts to the King, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtill a third part to the Inſtruments as were imployed about getting it in. It may well be doubted, that the King may have the like or worſe ſucceſſe in England: which appeares already in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p>The King hath reſerved upon this Monopoly of Wines, 30 thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pound Rent a yeere, the Vintner paies 40. Shillings a Tun, which comes to Ninty thouſand pounds: the price upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject by retaile, is increaſed Two pence a Quart, which comes to Eight pound a Tunne, and for 45000. Tunne brought in yeerely, amounts to 3. hundred 60. thouſand pounds, which is 3. hundred and 30. thouſand pounds loſſe to the Kingdome, above the Kings Rent; other Monopolies, as that of Soape, have been very charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the kingdome, and brought very little Treaſure into his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Coffers.</p>
            <p>The Law provides for that revenue of the Crowne; which is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:126020:12"/>
Naturall and proper, that it may be ſafely collected, and brought to Account, but this illegall Revenue, being without any ſuch provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is left to hazard, and much uncertainty, either not to be retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or not duly accounted of.</p>
            <p n="6">6 It is apt to weaken the Induſtry and Courage of the Subject, if <note place="margin">By weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry and courage of the ſubject.</note> they be left uncertain: whether they ſhall reap the benefit of their own paines, and hazard thoſe who are brought into the Condition of ſlaves, will eaſily grow to a ſlaviſh diſpoſition, who having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to loſe, doe commonly ſhew more boldneſſe in diſturbing, than in defending a kingdome.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Theſe irregular Courſes do give opportunity to ill Inſtruments <note place="margin">By introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ill In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments into the Kings ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</note> to inſinuate themſelves into the Kings ſervice, for wee cannot but obſerve, that if a man bee officious in furthering their inordinate burdens of Ship money, Monopolies, and the like: it varniſheth over all other faults, and makes him fit both for Imployment and preferment: So that out of their offices, they are furniſht for vaſt expences, purchaſes, Buildings; and the King loſeth often more in deſperate debts at their deaths, than he got by them all their lives, whether this were not lately verified in a Weſterne man, much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed while he lived, he leaves to the Knowledge of thoſe who w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re acquainted with his Courſe, and hee doubted not but others might be found in the like caſe.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are affected to Popery, to prophaneſſe, and to ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious innovations, in matters of Religion. All kinde of Spies and intelligencers have meanes to be countenanced and truſted if they will be but zealous in theſe kinde of ſervices, which how much it detracts from His Majeſtie, in honour, in profit and proſperity of publike affaires, lyes open to every mans apprehenſion: and from theſe reaſons or ſome of them, hee thought it proceeded that through the whole courſe of the Engliſh ſtory it might be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that thoſe Kings who had bin moſt reſpectfull of the Lawes, had bin moſt eminent in greatneſſe, in Glory and ſucceſſe, both at home and abroad; and that others, who thought to ſubſiſt by the viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, did often fall into a ſtate of weakneſſe, poverty, and Infortunitie.</p>
            <p n="8">8 The differences and diſcontents betwixt his Majeſtie, and the <note place="margin">By divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the KINGS thoughts from divers great and hopeful en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes.</note> people at home, have in all likely-hood diverted his Royal thoughts and Councells from thoſe great opportunities which hee might have, not only to weaken the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> to reſtore the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate,</hi> but to gaine to himſelf a higher pitch of power and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, than any of his Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:126020:13"/>
It is not unknown how weak, how diſtracted, how diſcontented the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Colonies are in the <hi>Weſt Indies.</hi> There are now in thoſe parts in New <hi>England, Virginia,</hi> and the <hi>Caribe-Iſlands,</hi> and in the <hi>Barmudos,</hi> at leaſt 60000 able perſons of this Nation, many of them well armed, and their bodies ſeaſoned to that Climate, which with a very ſmall charge might bee ſet down in ſome advantagious parts of theſe pleaſant, rich and fruitfull Countreys, and eaſily make his Majeſtie Maſter of all that treaſure, which not only foments the war, but is the great ſupport of Popery in all parts of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Laſtly, Thoſe courſes are apt to produce ſuch diſtempers in the <note place="margin">By produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing many chargeable diſtempers</note> ſtate, as may not be ſetled without great charge and loſſe, by which means more may be conſumed in a few moneths than ſhall be gotten by ſuch wayes in many yeeres.</p>
            <p>Having paſt through the two firſt generall Branches, he was now come to the third, wherein he was to ſet downe the wayes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <note place="margin">The wayes of remedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their grievances.</note> and removing thoſe grievances, which conſiſted of two maine Branches, firſt in declaring the Law where it was doubtfull: The ſecond in better proviſion for the execution of Law, where it is cleere: But (he ſaid) becauſe hee had already ſpent much time, and began to find ſome confuſion in his Memory, he would refer the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars to another opportunity, and for the preſent only move that, which was generall to all, and would give waight and advantage to all the particular wayes of redreſſe; that is, that we ſhould ſpeedily deſire a Conference with the Lords, and acquaint them with the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition wherein we find the Church and State, and as wee have already reſolved to joyn in a religious ſeeking of God, in a day of faſt and humiliation, ſo to intreat them to concur with us, in a Parliamentary courſe, of petitioning the King as there ſhould bee occaſion, and in ſearching out the cauſes and remedies of theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inſupportable grievances under which we lye, that ſo by the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wiſdome and authority of both Houſes, ſuch courſes may bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as (through Gods bleſſing) may advance the honour and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of His Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſty, and reſtore and eſtabliſh the peace and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>This (hee ſaid) Wee might undertake with comfort and hope of ſucceſſe: for though there bee a darkneſſe upon the Land, a thicke and palpable darkneſſe, like that of <hi>Egypt;</hi> yet as in that, the Sunne had not loſt his light, nor the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> their ſight, the interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was onely in the <hi>Medium,</hi> ſo with us there is ſtill (God bee thanked) light in the Sunne, Wiſdome and Juſtice in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to diſpell this darkneſſe, and in us there remaines a viſuall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:126020:13"/>
whereby wee are inabled to apprehend, and moved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire light, and when wee ſhall be bleſſed in the enjoying of it, we ſhall thereby be incited to returne His Majeſty ſuch thankes, as may make it thine more cleerely in the world, to His owne glory, and in the hearts of his people, to their joy and contentment.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
